# Kodjo KOUDAKPO

Tel: +1 438 221 4971 \$\display \text{Email: kodjo.koudakpo@umontreal.ca/kodjokoudakpo@yahoo.fr}

I am an Economist and Statistician interested in quantitative and qualitative analysis. My area of research involves macroeconomics, fiscal policy, and international economics. I have more than five years of international experience working on questions relating to development, fiscal and public policies, welfare, and poverty reduction. I have also worked on more than 50 national representative household surveys in Sub-Saharan Africa and I speak and write fluently English and French.

## PROFESSIONAL AND RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## **Economist-Statistician Consultant**

August 2023 - Now

World Bank Group, Macro, Trade, and Investment Global Practice

Washington D.C., USA

- · Multivariate cluster analysis of livelihood zones in Sahel countries (Niger, Mali, Burkina Faso, Chad)
- · Analytical work on quantitative livelihood zones in the Sahel using LMS survey data.

Research Assistant

May 2023 - July 2023

Observatoire de la Francophonie Economique,

Montreal, Canada

- · Research and technical assistance.
- · Analytical and technical contributions on the economic value of the Francophony in the World.

## **Economist-Statistician Consultant**

Feb 2023 - June 2023

World Bank Group, Poverty and Equity Global Practice

Washington D.C., USA

- · Analytical work on World Bank documents (Poverty assessment, PSIA, Analytical reports, etc).
- · Computation of multidimensional poverty, labor, education indicators, and other socio-demographic indicators in preparation for the Burundi poverty assessment.
- · Technical assistance to the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) Crisis Observatory Team on the project Impacts of COVID-19 on vulnerable populations.
- · Building and monitoring the DRC Crisis Observatory welfare and conflict track Tableau Dashboards and high-frequency database.
- · Production of technical and analytical inputs for the socio-economic profile of refugees in Burundi and the Eastern Democratic Republic of Congo.

## **Economist-Statistician Consultant**

July 2021 - June 2022

World Bank Group, Poverty and Equity Global Practice

Washington D.C., USA

- · Data quality assessment and validation of national household representative surveys.
- · Harmonization and analysis of 10 waves of COVID-19 High Phone Surveys (HFPS) in DRC.
- · Technical and analytical inputs to Madagascar HFPS surveys.
- · Analytical and technical contribution in the implementation of a social targeting program in DRC based on HFPS and Enterprise surveys.
- · Monitoring database on poverty, shared prosperity, labor, and education.
- · Technical support for statistical and data development in Africa and data-driven policies.

#### **Economist-Statistician Consultant**

July 2020 - June 2021

World Bank Group, Poverty and Equity Global Practice

Washington D.C., USA

- · Technical support for statistical and data development in Burundi.
- · Production of global database monitoring and analysis of the Iterative Beneficiary Monitoring Surveys in Burundi from the Social Safety Net project (Merankabandi).

- · Co-authored "Monitoring health service delivery in Burundi", with Alexandra Jarotschkin, Soazic E. W. Sonne, and Laura A. R. Rivera (2021), World Bank Group, Washington DC.
- · Designing, monitoring, and analysis of phone survey data collection in Burundi on the Social Safety Net projects (Kira and Merankabandi).
- · Training of the Burundi National Statistical Office Staff on poverty and shared prosperity analysis.

## Research Consultant

August 2020-November 2020

Research Technical Assistance Center, USAID

Washington, DC, USA

- · Co-authored "Poverty and Malnutrition in Haiti: Findings from Sud and Grand'Anse Departments", with Angelino Viceisza, Kodjo Aflagah, Atabanam Simbou, and Dixita Gupta (2020), Washington, DC.
- · Co-authored "Poverty and Malnutrition in Haiti: Findings from Nord-Est and Centre Departments", with Angelino Viceisza, Kodjo Aflagah, Atabanam Simbou, and Dixita Gupta (2020), Washington, DC.
- · Data quality assessment and validation of national representative DHS surveys in Haiti.
- · Research and technical assistance.

## **Economist-Statistician Consultant**

July 2019 - June 2020

World Bank Group, Poverty and Equity Global Practice

Washington D.C., USA

- · Assessment of water tariff reforms and poverty and social impacts analysis in Niger and Mali for internal communication.
- · Production of a global monitoring database on poverty, shared prosperity, labor, education, and other relevant socio-demographic indicators.
- · Harmonization and analysis of national representative LMS and household surveys.
- · Support for statistical and data development in Africa

# **Economist-Statistician Consultant**

Oct 2018 - June 2019

World Bank Group, Poverty and Equity Global Practice

Washington D.C., USA

- · Research and analytical inputs on the World Bank documents ( Poverty assessment, Systematic Country diagnostic, Poverty and Social Impact Analysis, Concepts Notes, etc).
- · Technical support to the Iterative Beneficial Monitoring (IBM) Team on Chad agricultural project.
- · Analytical work on the effect of spatial deflation on urban and rural poverty in more than 40 Sub-Saharan African countries from 2000 to 2019.

# Economist (Intern)

July 2017-October 2017

Central Bank of West African States, BCEAO-Headquarter

Dakar, Senegal

- · Analysis of the explanatory factors of the differences between the interest rates of the West African Economic and Monetary Union (WAEMU) member States
- · Developed software on RShiny to monitor indicators on the bank's conditions in the WAEMU

# Research Analyst

February 2016-June 2016

Laboratoire de Recherches Économiques et Monétaires, LAREM-UCAD

Dakar, Senegal

- · Analysis of the bank financing and performance of Small and Medium-sized Enterprises (SME) in Cameroon
- · Data processing, cleaning and analysis on the determinants of Cameroon's SMEs performance

#### Research Assistant

April 2015-June 2015

National School of Statistics and Economic Analysis (ENSAE)

Dakar, Senegal

- · Conception of the sampling technique for a census on production units in the areas of Louga
- · Data processing and cleaning

#### Research Assistant

July 2014- September 2014

Institut National de la Statistique, des Etudes Economiques et de la Démographie

Lome, Togo

- · Report on Youth Employment Characteristics in Togo
- · Data processing and cleaning
- · Training data collection agents

#### Research Assistant

April 2014- June 2014

National School of Statistics and Economic Analysis (ENSAE)

Dakar, Senegal

- · Training data collection agents on Survey on household access to primary health care services in Dakar
- · Data collection, processing, and cleaning

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

## Lecturer, University of Montreal

- · Econometrics (Undergraduate): Winter 2022
- · Introduction to Economics (Undergraduate): Fall 2022

# Teaching Assistant, University of Montreal

- · Econometrics (Undergraduate): Fall 2020, Winter 2021, Fall 2021, Winter 2023
- · Macroeconomic Theory (Undergraduate): Fall 2021, Fall 2022, Fall 2023
- · Introduction to Macroeconomics (Undergraduate): Summer 2023

## **EDUCATION**

## Ph.D. Candidate in Economics,

University of Montreal, Canada

2019 - August 2024

## M.Sc. in Statistics and Economics,

National School of Statistics and Economic Analysis (ENSAE), Senegal

2018

## B.Sc. in Applied Statistics,

National School of Statistic and Economic Analysis (ENSAE), Senegal

2016

## RESEARCH IN PROGRESS

- Fiscal rules and fiscal policy in developing economies
- o Geo-economic fragmentation: Implications for the global economy, (with Eklou Kodjovi)
- o Climate change and debt sustainability, (with Fansa Kone and Lucien Chaffa)

# POLICY PAPERS

- Monitoring health service delivery in Burundi, with Alexandra Jarotschkin, Soazic E. W. Sonne, and Laura A. R. Rivera (2021), World Bank Group, Washington DC.
- Poverty and Malnutrition in Haiti: Findings from Sud and Grand'Anse Departments, with Angelino Viceisza, Kodjo Aflagah, Atabanam Simbou, and Dixita Gupta (2020), Washington, DC.
- Poverty and Malnutrition in Haiti: Findings from Nord-Est and Centre Departments, with Angelino Viceisza, Kodjo Aflagah, Atabanam Simbou, and Dixita Gupta (2020), Washington, DC.

# FELLOWSHIPS, HONORS AND AWARDS

Ph.D. Fellowship, Department of Economics, University of Montreal	2019-Present
Ph.D. Fellowship, CIREQ, University of Montreal	2019-Present
World Bank Group VPU Team awards	2022
Tuition-fee waiver Scholarship, University of Montreal	2019-2021
Excellence Scholarship, United Nations Development Programme	2016-2018
Tuition-fee waiver Scholarship, ENSAE-Senegal	2012-2018
Excellence Scholarship, Odon-Vallet, ENSAE-Senegal	2012-2014

# CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS AND DISCUSSIONS

Société Canadienne de Science	Economique (SCSE): annual conference	May 2023
18th CIREQ Ph.D. Students' o	conference	May 2023
The Quebec Ph.D. weekly wor	kshop in Economics, Statistics, and Finance	2019-now
Macroeconomics weekly worksl	hop for Ph.D. Students at University of Montreal	2021-now

# SKILLS AND LANGUAGES

Statistical Software

Stata, Matlab, R, SPSS, Python, EVIEWS, SPAD, ArcGis, QGis

**Other software** Word, advanced Excel, VBA Excel, PowerPoint, Latex, CSPRO, EPI-Info, KoBo Data Kits, Tableau Dashboard

**Household surveys data** LMS & EHCVM (in more than 40 countries in Sub-Saharan Africa), DHS (Haiti, Madagascar), MICS (Madagascar)

Languages

English (Fluent), French (Native), Ewe (Native)

## **EXTRA-INFORMATION**

# Leadership roles

- · Member of CIREQ (Centre Interuniversitaire de Recherche en Economie Quantitative), Canada, 2020-present.
- · President of the Association of Togolese Students at ENSAE, Senegal, 2016-2017.
- · General Secretary of the Association of Togolese Students at ENSAE, Senegal, 2015-2016.
- $\cdot$  Treasurer of the Association of Togolese Students at ENSAE, Senegal, 2013-2015.

# Qualities

· Teamwork, ability to synthesize, communication and analysis skills, client orientation, passion for international development, data-driven person.

# Hobbies

· Traveling, Reading, Game of society, Football, Handball, and volleyball